Right, right.
Okay, we'll set that back. All right, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. All
right, so today's דף daf is דף ח, daf Chet, and we
pick up two lines from the
bottom, and אמר רב זריקא, Amar Rav Zreika, ומודים כששחט ציפור ודחו
יכסה. umodim ksheshachat tzippor ve'dacho yechase. So we're dealing with the debate
of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai about what
to do if you do not have prepared dirt to cover the
blood of a and you want to שחט shacht חיה chayah or
an עוף, of, like a deer or a chicken, for יום טוב.
Yom Tov. So first we dealt with the question of whether we
were talking about לכתחילה lechat'chila or בדיעבד. bidi'avad. We decided we were
talking about
לכתחילה, lechat'chila, that בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you can do it
לכתחילה lechat'chila and then just dig and cover it, and בית הלל
Beit Hillel says no you can't do it לכתחילה, lechat'chila, but they
agree if you went ahead and did it, then you can dig
and cover it. And now we're going to get to the issue
of how could you dig and cover it? Aren't there certain דרבנן
d'rabbanan at least rabbinic if not biblical problems with doing that on
יום טוב? Yom Tov? Because this isn't צורך אוכל נפש tzorech ochel
nefesh because the animal's already been שחט. shechted. You don't need to
do this in order to eat it; it's doing a מצוות עשה,
mitzvat asseh, but it's not necessary in order to make the food
edible; the food is כשר kosher without doing this. So how is
this allowed? So let's take a look. And let's take a look
at what the problem is. So two lines from the bottom on
ז עמוד ב, zayin amud bet, אמר רב זריקא אמר רב יהודה,
Amar Rav Zreika Amar Rav Yehuda, והוא שיש לו דקר נעוץ מבעוד
יום. vehu she'yesh lo dikar na'utz miba'od yom. So first of all,
you have to have the shovel stuck into the dirt from the
day before. Now that addresses the מוקצה muktzeh idea. Why isn't digging
the dirt... dirt is normally מוקצה, muktzeh, that's an issue that we'll
get to, you have no use for it. And this dirt wasn't
even like usable, it wasn't like loose dirt, it was like packed
into the ground. So how do you get around with the מוקצה
muktzeh idea? So it says you've got your shovel stuck in from
the day before. You knew you were going to שחט shecht and
dig. You didn't get around to digging and loosening up the dirt
beforehand, but the shovel's already there, so it's not a מוקצה muktzeh
issue. Okay, but how about like digging on יום טוב Yom Tov
is a problem beyond just מוקצה? muktzeh? So the גמרא Gemara says
והא קא עביד כתישה. ve'ha ka'avid tichsha.
You're grinding; you're taking the clumps of earth and sort of transforming
them into loose dirt, and that's sort of like טוחן. tochen. טוחן
Tochen is when you would take a piece of wheat and turn
it into flour. So it's a solid mass that you're turning into
like a more, you know, sort of pulverized, right, you're pulverizing it,
but yeah, you're turning it into what's like a dust-like type of
a, you know, loose type of a material and that's a type
of a, that's a type of a טוחן. tochen. So that's a
biblical prohibition. So it says אמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב,
Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi Amar Rav, בעפר תיחוח. be'afar tichuach. It's
loose dirt. All right, so you're really just digging loose dirt out
of a hole. You're not turning a clump of compressed clod of
earth into loose; it's already loose dirt. So the גמרא Gemara says
והא קא עביד גומא. ve'ha ka'avid gumma. All right, but at the
minimally you're making a hole. Now, you know, תוספות Tosafot discusses it
means that it's like you could have two scenarios of loose dirt.
You could have loose dirt, loose sand in a sandbox where you
take it and you don't make a hole because there's no like
solid dirt around it, right, so everything just sort of shifts and
you don't make a hole at all. But here, if you have
like loose dirt in or surrounded by solid earth, when you dig
it out you're making a hole. And isn't that a problem? Because
why is making a hole a problem? Making a hole could be
one of two problems on יום טוב Yom Tov or on שבת.
Shabbat. One is that it's בונה; boneh; you're creating something, you're creating
a hole in the ground that's usable; you can store things in
it. The other thing is is that if it's in a type
of a field that's made for planting and it's in a way
that's possible for planting, then it's a type of a חורש, choreish,
it's a plowing. So aren't making a hole... isn't that a מלאכה
melacha on יום טוב? Yom Tov? So the גמרא Gemara says כרבי
אבא ke'Rabbi Abba like רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba, דאמר רבי אבא, d'amar
Rabbi Abba, החופר גומא בשבת ואין צריך אלא לעפרה. hachofer gumma be'Shabbat
ve'ein tzarich ela la'afarah.
Almost exactly the same case. It could have been tailor-made to explain
this case. You dig a hole in the ground on שבת Shabbat
but you're not interested in the hole; you're interested in the dirt.
And the מלאכה melacha is because of the hole, that the hole
is either creating a
בונה, boneh, something for, it's a structure, something to place things in,
or because it's for planting. But here you're not interested in the
hole; the hole is a byproduct of your extraction of dirt. So
the הלכה halacha is פטור patur because that's called מלאכה שאינה צריכה
לגופה. melacha she'eina tzricha legufa. It's a מלאכה, melacha, but what your
intention was was not the same as the purpose, the defined purpose
of the מלאכה. melacha. The defined purpose of the מלאכה melacha is
making a hole. For you, that was a byproduct. Your intention, your
צריך tzarich was not לגופה, legufa, was not for the basic purpose
of the מלאכה, melacha, but was for a different intention and this
was just a byproduct. Now that minimally is forbidden דרבנן. d'rabbanan. So
how are we allowing it here?
So רש"י Rashi throws in here, he says, if you look at
רש"י, Rashi, אלא מקלקל, ela mekalkel, third line from the top, וכל
המקלקלין פטורין. ve'chol hame'kalkelin paturin. רש"י Rashi throws in here that it's
not just מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, melacha she'eina tzricha legufa, it's also
קלקול, kilkul, and that makes it even, you know, it's sort of
destructive to the ground and that makes it even more lenient. תוספות
Tosafot basically says obviously we're giving you a certain amount of latitude
to be מקיים mekayyem the biblical מצוה mitzvah of כיסוי הדם. kissuy
hadam. דם, dam, but we have to get it down to a
דרבנן D'rabanan problem. Okay, so if you take a look at the
תוספות Tosfos אינה צריכה אלא לעפר פטור, Eina tzericha ela la'afar patur,
תוספות Tosfos says משום דהוי מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה ופטור אבל אסור
לכתחילה. mishum d'havei melacha she'eina tzericha legufa u'patur aval assur lechatchila. So
for that רש"י'ס Rashi's answer was קלקול kilkul which makes it better.
תוספות Tosfos says ויש לומר דמשום שמחת יום טוב מותר אפילו לכתחילה.
v'yesh lomar d'mishum simchas yom tov mutar afilu lechatchila. All right, we
give you that allowance, that's not across the board, as we're about
to see in the next line of תוספות. Tosfos. And it's funny,
it's called משום שמחת יום טוב, mishum simchas yom tov, right? Not
because of the מצוה mitzvah of כיסוי הדם, Kisui HaDam, but presumably
if we make it hard for you to do כיסוי הדם, Kisui
HaDam, it'll be hard for you to שחט. shecht. Although, again, it's
funny, because according to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, you're not supposed to
שחט shecht anyway. So framing it as שמחת יום טוב simchas yom
tov once it was already done is a little funny. But anyway,
even that is not a blanket allowance because he then says, ואם
תאמר אם כן למה לי דקר נעוץ, v'im tomar im kein lama
li dakar na'utz, why did you need the shovel stuck in the
ground from beforehand? ויש לומר דמכל מקום בעינן שיהא מוכן מערב יום
טוב, v'yesh lomar d'mikal makom ba'inan sheyehei muchan me'erev yom tov,
which is a little bit of a begs the question, doesn't exactly
say why. Somehow the issue of מוקצה muktzah we're not going to
override. Like you need to address the מוקצה muktzah issue. You got
to have your shovel stuck in, you have to make sure that
it's not מוקצה. muktzah. But once you've addressed the מוקצה muktzah issue,
and the only issue is an issue of, you know, digging a
hole which you're not allowed to do, well, it's only a מלאכה
שאינה צריכה לגופה, melacha she'eina tzericha legufa, we'll allow it. Which is
pretty funny. You would think that if you wanted to be strict,
you'd be strict on the thing which more bordered on the מלאכה
melacha as opposed to something which was just an issue of a
דרבנן D'rabanan of מוקצה. muktzah. But anyway, we will see as we
continue this issue about the מוקצה muktzah thing, but the גמרא Gemara
here is giving some latitude to something that normally would be forbidden.
Yes, Charlie?
Nobody's bringing up פסיק רישא. psik reisha. You're guaranteed to make a
hole.
Yeah, so the question is in general, which I'm not going to
get into right now, that every case of דבר שאינו מתכוין davar
she'eino miskavein פסיק רישא psik reisha could be redefined as a מלאכה
שאינה צריכה לגופה, melacha she'eina tzericha legufa, right? I'm dragging the chair
across the flowerbed. So if it's a פסיק רישא psik reisha at
such a heavy chair on a loose flowerbed that it'll definitely make
a furrow, that's called oh, that's already not allowed because אינו מתכוין
eino miskavein because that's a פסיק רישא. psik reisha. Okay, but why
don't you just call the combination of אינו מתכוין eino miskavein פסיק
רישא, psik reisha, I'm not trying to do it, I'm trying to
do something else, it'll definitely come out, that's a מלאכה שאינה צריכה
לגופה, melacha she'eina tzericha legufa, right? So shouldn't that be the case?
So actually according to some it is, according to the בעל המאור
Ba'al HaMaor they basically are the same. And the only problem of
פסיק רישא psik reisha is when it's ניחא ליה, nicha leih, you
want the end result. Because but in the case of מלאכה שאינה
צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzericha legufa which you're exempt for is when
you're not interested in the hole, לא ניחא ליה. lo nicha leih.
But if there's a ניחא ליה, nicha leih, then that does make
a problem. But you are correct that a normal אינו מתכוין eino
miskavein plus פסיק רישא psik reisha seems to be the same as
as מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eina tzericha legufa. There is an
attempt to try to distinguish between those cases, but I'm not going
to get into that right now.
Yes. תוספות Tosfos also doesn't use the language of מוקצה, muktzah, use
the language of מוכן. muchan. מוכן. Muchan. In all these סוגיות, sugyos,
have we seen a clear definition that מוקצה muktzah is something that
we have no other use for?
No, all we've seen, by the way, it seems that, and I
haven't double checked that, there are two terms going on which I
discussed earlier, one is מוכן muchan and אינו מן המוכן, eino min
hamuchan, and the other is מוקצה. muktzah. It seems that the idea
of מוכן muchan and אינו מן המוכן eino min hamuchan is earlier,
is from the בית הלל Beis Hillel בית שמאי Beis Shammai period,
whereas מוקצה muktzah it seems to me, again I'm not promising this,
I could be wrong, but impressionistically is later, like from the רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva period. I could be wrong.
They do describe two different approaches. מוקצה Muktzah is the more lenient
approach. מוקצה Muktzah says basically everything is okay except those things that
are specifically pushed away. You have to define the category of things
that are off-limits, only things that are מוקצה. muktzah. מוכן Muchan is
the opposite, you have to define the category of everything that's okay,
only things that are מוכן muchan or theoretically מוכן, muchan, but still
you have to make it okay rather than make it not okay.
So anyway, we'll the language here is much more a language of
מוכן, muchan, which roughly correlates to the מוקצה muktzah issue, but not
exactly. Yes.
Now one more, if if I stick the shovel in the ground
before שבת, Shabbos, I've already started making the hole, and therefore I'm
not doing an entire...
Doesn't matter. What, if I start writing a sentence in my book,
I can finish writing my book on שבת? Shabbos?
It's like the pre-perforated toilet paper issue.
That's a different issue.
What happens to everything in between that which is prepared and that
which is not?
Right, so that's the issue. So if if we're so
הלכה Halacha we פסקן pasken really מוקצה muktzah more than this idea
of מוכן, muchan, but even if you do this idea of מוכן,
muchan, you don't need to actively go around your house and start
designating. You know, we sort of get a lot of stuff in
by things that were you to have stopped and thought about it
or things under normal circumstances you would want to use that's called
מוכן muchan as well. But even so, there's still by demanding מוכן
muchan you're allowing fewer things than by identifying מוקצה. muktzah. Okay, let's
take a look now as the גמרא Gemara continues.
So it says like this, שיהא דקר נעוץ מבעוד יום. Sheyehei dakar
na'utz miba'od yom. So if you can go ahead and dig.
Because the ashes from an oven are prepared. So what's that because,
right? We just talked about digging a hole. So the גמרא Gemara
says אפר כירה מאן דכר שמיא? efer kera man dechar shemaya? Ashes
of an oven, who mentioned it? "Because the ashes of an oven."
So אמר רבה הכי קאמר, Amar Rabah hachi kama, this is what
it means. זה אפר כירה מוכן הוא. zeh efer kera muchan hu.
It doesn't mean שאפר. she'efer. It means and you should also be
aware that if you don't want to dig a hole and you
have ashes of your oven, you can use the ashes of your
oven. That's considered, again, here's the phrase, מוכן הוא. muchan hu. It's
not אינו מן המוכן, eino min hamuchan, it is מוכן. muchan. So
מוכן muchan here has that technical sense meaning, you know, not מוקצה,
muktzah, able to be used on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom
Tov. Okay, שאפר כירה מוכן הוא. she'efer kera muchan hu. So therefore
that could also be used for your covering. Now by the way,
there's a תוספות Tosafot has a problem because he says this is
part of the thing that בית שמאי Beit Shammai agrees on and
he quotes the גמרא Gemara in חולין Chulin that it sounds like
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you can't use ashes to do כיסוי
הדם. kisuy hadam. So that's a little bit of a problem. Whoops.
So okay, it's not מוקצה muktzah but you're allowed to... so he
tries to distinguish between different types of ashes. We're not going to
go into that, I just wanted to note that for the record.
Okay, so now the גמרא's Gemara going to say like this.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, לא שנו
אלא שהוסק מערב יום טוב. lo shanu ela shehusak me'erev Yom Tov.
So this, when is it that ashes are considered מוכן muchan if
you lit the fire ערב יום טוב? erev Yom Tov? So meaning
it was already ashes when יום טוב Yom Tov began. But don't
say that ashes are something that like, you know, that you have
no use for, ashes is something you'll just throw out. No, if
you already had ashes in the oven when יום טוב Yom Tov
began, ashes are stuff that you might have a use for around
the house and that's considered not מוקצה. muktzah.
אבל, Aval, one minute, אבל
הוסק ביום טוב,
aval
husak
beYom Tov, and again, by יום טוב Yom Tov we can have
these interesting scenarios because you're allowed to make a fire on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. If it was burnt on יום טוב Yom Tov
and the ashes were created on יום טוב, Yom Tov, אסור. assur.
Then it's forbidden because that already, even though you tend to have
uses for ashes, but the ashes is something new. When יום טוב
Yom Tov began it was wood and now you have ashes. And
it's sort of like again like the egg that was laid and
so on, which is even if you knew you were going to
use the firewood and you knew it was going to become ashes,
it didn't yet exist yet to be considered מוכן. muchan. And therefore
this newly created ashes is not something that you could use. However
it goes on to say, ואם ראוי לצלות בו ביצה, ve'im ra'uy
litzlot bo beitzah, let's say the ashes are still hot enough and
there's enough substance to them that you can still cook an egg
in the ashes, then מותר, mutar, it's permissible. Why is the fact
that they're hot make it permissible? And the basic logic is is
they haven't totally transformed. Exactly. Since it started יום טוב Yom Tov
as wood and what do you use wood for? You use wood
for making a fire, holding a fire, cooking things, and these ashes
are still in that category. They're still functioning like the wood, they're
holding the heat and they could be used for cooking. So in
that type of way they're slightly transformed wood but they're still wood.
They aren't yet something totally new and therefore they're considered מוכן. muchan.
But once they've completely changed and now they're just dead ashes, now
there's something that's different and they are not able to be used
if they were newly created on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So you
had a question. רש"י Rashi actually answered it. רש"י Rashi adds here
that you have to have had in mind from before יום טוב
Yom Tov you're going to use these ashes in order to cover
the blood. So there's a כוונה kavanah issue. That's not so clear.
What רש"י Rashi says, שהוסק מאתמול דעתיה עילויה? shehusak me'etmol daitey ilavey?
No, דעתיה עילויה, daitey ilavey, and that's what we're going to see
and that gets back to this question of what מוכן muchan means.
Nobody ever says מוכן muchan means you have to go around and
designate and specifically consciously say I'm going to use this, I'm going
to use this, I'm going to use that. דעתיה עילויה daitey ilavey
means yeah it's something that you would think of, like if somebody
would stop and say to you, you didn't consciously think about it
for one second, but if I was to stop and say to
you Dov, do you think it's possible you might have some uses
for your ashes over יום טוב? Yom Tov? He says yeah if
I ever needed them I'd use them. So דעתיה עילויה daitey ilavey
just means like you know not necessarily even your conscious דעת da'at
is on it. Yeah, it just means like I mean you could
say it that way but it doesn't mean like we would have
to ask you and if you said to me you know I
never stopped for a second before יום טוב Yom Tov to think
about the fact that I might use the
ashes, like it doesn't matter. As a general principle is this a
type of a thing that you tend to use around the house?
Yes. So that's דעתיה עילויה. daitey ilavey. As a general principle it's
a thing I know that
I anticipate I might have a need to use. Okay that's basically
how this is to be understood. The גמרא Gemara never says it
says you have to consciously do it. Okay let's take a look.
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught something similar. כשאמרו אפר
כירה מוכן הוא, keshe'amru efer kera muchan hu, when they said ashes
of an oven are מוכן, muchan, meaning so they're able to be
used, not אינו מן המוכן. eino min hamuchan. So לא אמרו אלא
שהוסק מערב יום טוב. lo amru ela shehusak me'erev Yom Tov. That's
they only said this when it was burnt turned into ashes before
יום טוב. Yom Tov. So once even though it's ashes don't say
ashes is like the smelly garbage and it's not מן המוכן. min
hamuchan. No it's a type of thing that you would have a
reason to use. אבל הוסק ביום טוב, aval husak beYom Tov, and
again, by יום טוב Yom Tov we can have these interesting scenarios
because you're allowed to make a fire on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
If it was burnt on יום טוב Yom Tov and the ashes
were created on יום טוב, Yom Tov, אסור. assur. Then it's forbidden
because that already, even though you tend to have uses for ashes,
but the ashes is something new. When יום טוב Yom Tov began
it was wood and now you have ashes. And it's sort of
like again like the egg that was laid and so on, which
is even if you knew you were going to use the firewood
and you knew it was going to become ashes, it didn't yet
exist yet to be considered מוכן. muchan. And therefore this newly created
ashes is not something that you could use. However it goes on
to say, ואם ראוי לצלות בו ביצה, ve'im ra'uy litzlot bo beitzah,
let's say the ashes are still hot enough and there's enough substance
to them that you can still cook an egg in the ashes,
then מותר, mutar, it's permissible. Why is the fact that they're hot
make it permissible? And the basic logic is is they haven't totally
transformed. Exactly. Since it started יום טוב Yom Tov as wood and
what do you use wood for? You use wood for making a
fire, holding a fire, cooking things, and these ashes are still in
that category. They're still functioning like the wood, they're holding the heat
and they could be used for cooking. So in that type of
way they're slightly transformed wood but they're still wood. They aren't yet
something totally new and therefore they're considered מוכן. muchan. But once they've
completely changed and now they're just dead ashes, now there's something that's
different and they are not able to be used if they were
newly created on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So you had a question.
רש"י Rashi actually answered it. רש"י Rashi adds here that you have
to have had in mind from before יום טוב Yom Tov you're
going to use these ashes in order to cover the blood. So
there's a כוונה kavanah issue. That's not so clear. What רש"י Rashi
says, שהוסק מאתמול דעתיה עילויה? shehusak me'etmol daitey ilavey? No, דעתיה עילויה,
daitey ilavey, and that's what we're going to see and that gets
back to this question of what מוכן muchan means. Nobody ever says
מוכן muchan means you have to go around and designate and specifically
consciously say I'm going to use this, I'm going to use this,
I'm going to use that. דעתיה עילויה daitey ilavey means yeah it's
something that you would think of, like if somebody would stop and
say to you, you didn't consciously think about it for one second,
but if I was to stop and say to you Dov, do
you think it's possible you might have some uses for your ashes
over יום טוב? Yom Tov? He says yeah if I ever needed
them I'd use them. So דעתיה עילויה daitey ilavey just means like
you know not necessarily even your conscious דעת da'at is on it.
Yeah, it just means like I mean you could say it that
way but it doesn't mean like we would have to ask you
and if you said to me you know I never stopped for
a second before יום טוב Yom Tov to think about the fact
that I might use the ashes, like it doesn't matter. As a
general principle is this a type of a thing that you tend
to use around the house? Yes. So that's דעתיה עילויה. daitey ilavey.
As a general principle it's a thing I know that I anticipate
I might have a need to use. Okay that's basically how this
is to be understood. The גמרא Gemara never says it says you
have to consciously do it. Okay
let's take a look. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught
something similar. כשאמרו אפר כירה מוכן הוא, keshe'amru efer kera muchan hu,
when they said ashes of an oven are מוכן, muchan, meaning so
they're able to be used, not אינו מן המוכן. eino min hamuchan.
So לא אמרו אלא שהוסק מערב יום טוב. lo amru ela shehusak
me'erev Yom Tov. That's they only said this when it was burnt
turned into ashes before יום טוב. Yom Tov. So once even though
it's ashes don't say ashes is like the smelly garbage and it's
not מן המוכן. min hamuchan. No it's a type of thing that
you would have a reason to use. אבל הוסק ביום טוב, aval
husak beYom Tov, if it was newly created on יום טוב, Yom
Tov, so in that case. אסור, asur, it's forbidden. But דראוי לצלות
בו ביצה מותר, De-rauy litzlos bo betza mutar, if you can still
cook an egg on it, then it's permissible because then again it's
not like something new, it's more like a slightly transformed piece of
wood, but it still is like the original piece of wood. Okay,
and now we go on. הכניס עפר לגינתו, Hichnis afar leginato, this
is presumably is the continuation of the ברייתא. braita. If you bring
in dirt into your garden ולחורבתו u-lechurvato or into your sort of
like alley, your yard, מותר לכסות בה, mutar lechasos bah, you can
use it to cover, to cover the blood with it because then
basically you've got a pile of dirt, all-purpose dirt. Like you know,
it really brings you into varied realities, right? Dirt was a very
usable thing. You could use it for a lot of stuff, used
it to cover up some smelly thing, you can use it for,
I don't know, filling in holes. So you got a pile of
dirt in your yard there, in your garden there, it's some nice
all-purpose dirt. So the whole point is it's all-purpose dirt and therefore
it's מוכן, muchan, it's stuff you have a, who knows, any use
you'll have for it, you'll use it for. So that type of
dirt you don't need to have a shovel stuck in from the
day before, whatever, that's the type of thing you can clearly is
not מוקצה muktzeh and you can use for כיסוי הדם. kisuy hadam.
Now ואמר רב יהודה, ve-amar Rav Yehuda, now says also רב יהודה,
Rav Yehuda, and it's not so clear what how this is really
different than what we just said before.
מכניס אדם מלוא קופתו עפר, Machnis adam melo kupato afar, a person
can bring in a basketful or boxful of dirt, like maybe into
the house ועושה בה כל צרכו ve-oseh bah kol tzorcho and use
it for any purpose. So how's that different than this big pile
of dirt in your garden? So רש״י Rashi says it's a smaller
pile like, you know, that garden you'd have a big pile so
clearly it's like set aside for any use you might have whereas
this is a
boxful, it's not so big, it's not so big. Maybe if it's
sitting there on the ground, it's, you know, if you had a
dirt floor pretty soon it'll become incorporated into the ground itself. So
the חידוש chiddush here is that even though it's not such a
big pile, it's still allowed. The other part of the חידוש chiddush
here is כל צרכו, kol tzorcho, which is like if you bring
in, "Hey honey, look what I picked up in the store, a
box of dirt!" You know, perfect, perfect, we can use it for
so many things. And you bring it into your house for that
type of purpose. Like why are you bringing dirt into the house?
Right? Because it's not out in the field, out in the field
you know why you need dirt. Anyway, you bring it into the
house, it's to serve as all-purpose, for any purpose, כל צרכו. kol
tzorcho. So like meaning, you know, some types of things we might
just say, well that's the type of thing you would expect to
use for X but not for Y. Like if you've got dirt
in your yard, maybe you would use it to fill up holes
or you'd use it to cover the blood if you שחט shacht
animals in your backyard, but you wouldn't necessarily use it, I don't
know, for a sandbox. That's not what you use dirt in your
yard for, the pile of dirt. But if you bring a box
of dirt into your house, there it's כל צרכו, kol tzorcho, it's
any type of use you might have is on the table. So
let's see sort of what where the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
Yes. Cat litter.
Yeah. Oh, good. Basically dirt.
Right. So again, totally fine. Anything that is, has set aside for
a function is like not מוקצה. muktzeh. There's nothing that's dirt is
objectively מוקצה, muktzeh, right? I mean the sandbox is not מוקצה, muktzeh,
it's set aside for playing. Right? So now the question, so let's
take a
look. So you know, it is an interesting question, could you use
like the sand of a sandbox to do other things with because
sand of a sandbox is like, it's not cheap to get that
type of sand, right? It's not just סתם stam dirt. So can
you use it for something you would use סתם stam dirt for?
Covering blood of a, of an animal.
Exactly. Right, exactly. Sandbox. So alright. So the גמרא Gemara says that's
part of the חידוש chiddush of כל צרכו, kol tzorcho, this dirt
in the house is considered to be usable for anything. So okay,
let's take a look. דרש מר זוטרא משמיה דמר זוטרא רבה, Darash
Mar Zutra mishmei de-Mar Zutra Rabba, so מר זוטרא Mar Zutra taught
in the name of מר זוטרא Mar Zutra the elder, והוא שיחד
לו קרן זוית. ve-hu she-yichad lo keren zavit. That's only if it
has its own corner because if it doesn't have its own corner
and it's a small amount of dirt inside the house, pretty soon
it's going to get spread on the ground and incorporated into the
ground. So in order to sort of see it as something distinct
from the ground and something there for general use, it has to
have like this, you know, this is where the pile of dirt
lives, it's in this corner right over here. אוקיי, מיתיבי. Okay, meitivi.
Now I'm going to ask you on this that there's this idea
that you can have something that's really completely not מוקצה, muktzeh, able
to be used for anything. כוי, Koy, if you have a כוי,
koy, the same is כוי koy which is this animal which is,
which was indeterminate whether it was in the חיה chaya category or
the בהמה behema category. The domesticator or non-domesticator. Why does it matter?
Well there's two ways in which הלכתית halachically in which a חיה
chaya is different than a בהמה. behema. Number one is you have
to cover the blood of a חיה chaya and number two is
that you are allowed to eat the fat of a חיה. chaya.
You can't eat the חלב chelev of a בהמה behema because that
חלב chelev would normally go על המזבח. al hamizbeach. But you can
eat the חלב chelev of a חיה. chaya. So if this thing
is a חיה, chaya, you have to cover the blood, but you
can eat the fat. And if it's a בהמה, behema, the reverse
is true. Now can you שחט shacht it on יום טוב? Yom
Tov? Because you would have to cover the blood but you might
not be חייב chayav in covering the blood, so would we be
allowed to give you that latitude that we gave normally somebody to
cover the blood in this case when it's only doubtful? Now remember,
according
to
בית הלל...
Beit Hillel... Yeah.
So כוי, Koy, I mean they must do it, you go to
like Empire whatever, yeah, you gotta do it. Okay, כוי Koy אין
שוחטין אותו ביום טוב, ein shochtin oso b'Yom Tov, don't שחט shecht
it on יום טוב Yom Tov because then you'll put yourself in
this situation of not being sure whether you have to cover the
blood. ואם שחטו, ve-im shachto, if you did שחט shecht it, אין
מכסין את דמו, ein mechassin es damo, בדיעבד be-diavad we won't let
you cover the blood, because presumably covering the blood will involve some
type of a violation, a minor violation which we'll allow for a
case of a ודאי, vadai, but we won't allow for a case
of a ספק. safek. That seems to be the point. Okay, now,
ואי איתא ve-i issa now presumably if this were the case about
the rooster in the hole, then we understand what's going on, right?
Because there as we just said, we're going to give you a
certain latitude that generally should be problematic, it's like making a hole
מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, melachah she-einah tzerichah l'gufah, but we'll let you
do it, you need to cover the blood, בדיעבד be-diavad you shouldn't
have done it but you did it, cover the blood. But by
a כוי Koy we won't give you that latitude because it's not
a—it's not necessarily an obligation. That makes sense. We just saw that
we'll give you a little latitude בדיעבד be-diavad if we need to
in order to cover the blood, but not for a כוי. Koy.
But the גמרא Gemara says, I don't get it. The גמרא Gemara
says, who needs any latitude? I can give you a very common
scenario, you have a pile of dirt in your house, which there's
no latitude needed, there's no מוקצה, muktzah, there's no digging of a
hole, what's the whole problem? And presumably this was a very common
scenario, so for רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda right, what should the issue
be? ואי איתא ve-i issa and if it—if it's true what רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda said, לכסיה כדרב יהודה, lechasyia k'derav Yehuda, cover it
like what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda suggested. So why should this whole
thing be a problem? רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda a common scenario and
it would be a case where there'd be no מוקצה, muktzah, no
concerns, so do it even for the כוי. Koy. So the גמרא
Gemara says ולטעמיך, u-l'ta'amecha, and according to you that you don't like
רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda idea that this dirt could be usable for
anything, nevertheless there are still other options with a כוי. Koy. לכסיה
באפר כירה, lechasyia b'eifer kirah, how about using ashes that were in
the oven from the day before? That's completely not problematic, right? There's
no hole making, there's no מוקצה, muktzah, there are other options that
are non-problematic which you should be able to use for a כוי.
Koy. או בדקר נעוץ, o b'dekar na'utz, or with the stuck-in shovel.
Now that תוספות Tosafos takes those words out for various—for other reasons,
but because anyway there—there's an easier answer, the stuck-in shovel is problematic,
right? The stuck-in shovel is making a hole and מלאכה שאינה צריכה
לגופה melachah she-einah tzerichah l'gufah and so on. It's not non-problematic, but
at least the ashes of the oven is okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says, I don't get it, why should you not שחט shecht
this כוי? Koy? According to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda just use the
pile of dirt. And the response back is, forget רב יהודה, Rav
Yehuda, why not שחט shecht just use ashes? Right? So what's the
problem? There are things which aren't—don't require any rule-bending that would allow
me to cover the blood. So why shouldn't I be able to
do the כוי Koy that way as well? אלא דלית ליה, ela
d'leis lei, we must say we're talking in a case where you
don't have ashes to use and we're saying if you don't have
ashes and the only thing you could do is dig the hole,
don't dig the hole. הכא נמי דלית ליה, hacha nami d'leis lei,
here too that we're talking that you don't have a pile of
dirt. Okay, so it's a case where you don't have ashes, you
don't have a pile of dirt, and therefore it's saying don't שחט
shecht this כוי Koy because that would require a certain יום טוב
Yom Tov violation. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, אי
הכי, ei hachi, if that's true that you don't have ashes and
you don't have dirt, מאי איריא ספק? mai irya safek? Why are
you just telling me not שחט shecht the כוי? Koy? אפילו ודאי
נמי לא, afilu vadai nami lo, you can't even שחט shecht a
normal חיה. chayah. Why not? Because we're talking according to בית הלל,
Beis Hillel, right? What does בית הלל Beis Hillel say? If you
don't have ashes, you only have the shovel and you'd have to
dig a hole, בית הלל Beis Hillel says don't שחט. shecht. בדיעבד
be-diavad I'll let you שחט, shecht, but don't שחט. shecht. So if
you wanted to make a difference בדיעבד, be-diavad, בדיעבד be-diavad I already
שחטed, shecht can I dig the hole or not? And we would
say well by a בהמה behemah yes, but by a כוי Koy
no, that I get. But if we're talking about that all you
have, you don't have ashes, you don't have dirt, all you got
is the shovel in the hole, then both a כוי Koy and
a בהמה behemah the answer is the same, לכתחילה l'chatchilah don't do
it. So what's the difference? אפילו ודאי נמי לא. afilu vadai nami
lo. So the גמרא Gemara says לא מיבעיא קאמר, lo mibaya ka'amar,
no, we're saying it goes without saying, meaning לא מיבעיא ודאי דלא
לישחוט, lo mibaya vadai d'lo lishchot, certainly you can't שחט shecht a
ודאי vadai because that'll put you in a position that you'll have
to dig the hole, so בית הלל Beis Hillel doesn't want you
to שחט shecht a ודאי vadai לכתחילה l'chatchilah if you'd have to
dig a hole. אבל
ספק, aval safek, but I'll come and say to you like this,
oh I got a solution, I'll שחט shecht the כוי Koy and
therefore that you should let me do, אימא משום שמחת יום טוב
לשחוט ולא לכסיה. eima mishum simchas Yom Tov lishchot v'lo lechasyia. You
come to the רב Rav and say, look we פסק pasken like
בית הלל, Beis Hillel, don't שחט shecht your deer because you'll have
to dig the hole. Oh I got an idea, let me שחט
shecht my כוי Koy and then it'll only be a ספק safek
if I have to dig the hole and I won't dig the
hole and no big deal, so I won't cover the blood, but
you know maybe I don't even have to cover the blood. So
I mean you're suggesting to do it without covering the blood, maybe
we should let you do it לכתחילה l'chatchilah without covering the blood,
okay? קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that no, we're not going
to let you get into that situation. You want to שחט shecht
your cow, fine, but we're not going to let you do the
כוי Koy that way as well. You want to שחט shacht *shecht*
your cow fine, but you want to שחט shechted *shecht* your deer?
No, because you'll have to cover the blood. You want to שחט
shechting *shecht* your כוי koi *koy* without covering the blood? No, we're
not going to let you שחט *shecht* a כוי koi, *koy* without
covering the blood, so we're not going to let you שחט *shecht*
the כוי koi. *koy*. Okay, so now how have we explained this
ברייתא *braita*? We're talking that you don't have nice prepared dirt or
ashes to use, so it's going to be a problem because you'll
have to dig that hole. And therefore we're saying don't do it
by a בהמה beheimah, *behema* that will force you to dig the
hole. Don't do it by a
חיה chaya *chaya*, you'll have to dig the hole. Don't do it
by a כוי koi *koy* and suggest not digging the hole, that's
not acceptable either. But if you went ahead and you did שחט
*shecht* it, then by a חיה chaya *chaya* dig the hole, by
a כוי koi *koy* not. But לכתחילה *lechatchila* you shouldn't be שחט
*shecht*-ing either. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this:
והא מדקתני סיפא *veha midkatni seifa*, one minute, the end of it
says, ואם שחטו אין מכסין את דמו *v'im shechato ein mechassin et
damo*, if you שחט *shecht* it, you cannot cover the blood. מכלל
דביש ליה עסקינן *michlal d'vish lei askinan*, so you see that we're
talking about that you do have something to cover it with. Okay,
because it says don't cover, which means that there is a possibility
of covering. So how could you say that there is no possibility
of covering? Now again, it's hard to understand what that question is,
because it could be there's a possibility of covering by digging a
hole, and that's what we'll allow by the case of a חיה
chaya *chaya* and we won't allow by the case of a כוי
koy, *koy*. Okay, so רש״י Rashi *Rashi* tells us, tries to figure
out exactly what's bothering this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. But רש״י *Rashi* reads
it as the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* literally thinks that there's absolutely nothing,
you can't even dig a hole, like there's no shovel stuck in
or whatever. אלא אמר רבא Ella amar Rava: *ela amar Rava*, so
therefore again, not exactly clear why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is rejecting
that read of the ברייתא *braita*, which is a completely reasonable read
of the ברייתא *braita*, that's just saying בדיעבד *bedi'avad* in one case
dig the hole, in the other case don't. But rather anyway, רבא
Rava *Rava* says, אפר eifer כירה מוכן muchan. לודאי ואין מוכן muchan
לספק *eifer kira muchan l'vadai v'ein muchan l'safeik*. So we're going to
go back and say fine, maybe you did have ashes. So why
can't I use the ashes to cover by the כוי koy *koy*?
If ashes are considered מוכן muchan *muchan*, because they are מוכן muchan
*muchan* for things that have a definite need, they're not מוכן muchan.
*muchan* for things that only have a doubtful need. Now that I
got to tell you is pretty funny. You know, it's like even
if the reason I'm doing it is because I have a doubtful
obligation, the sort of doubtful obligation creates a ודאי vaday. *vadai* need,
right?
I maybe have a חיוב *chiyuv* to cover the blood. Because of
the fact that I maybe have a חיוב *chiyuv* to cover the
blood means right now I have to cover the blood. Okay? In
practical terms. Whether in halachic terms I have a חיוב *chiyuv* we
don't know, but practically that means that I got to cover the
blood. So why should my ashes not be... I not be think
that I'm going to be able to use my ashes for a
similar type of a need? Unless it gets back to this issue
of that it's not like you have a generic intention in your
head like I'll use it for whatever. That gets back to the
dirt. They said if you have a box of dirt, it's generic
and you can use it for whatever. But maybe ashes, it's how
many things do you use ashes for? ערב תשעה באב *erev Tisha
B'Av*, you get a... חתונה *chatuna*, you have that מנהג *minhag*. How
many things do you use ashes for? So maybe it's saying that
for ashes, you know, the only thing it's מוכן muchan *muchan* for
are the things you expect to use it for because there's very
few things. And one of those things would be שחט *shecht*-ing a
חיה chaya. *chaya*, but you wouldn't expect to use it for a
כוי koy, *koy*. So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. I
understand if we didn't have רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* and the idea
that dirt could be used for כל צרכיו kol tzorachav. *kol tzrachov*,
anything under the sun. So ashes maybe we'll say you intend to
use it for a חיה chayah *chaya*, you don't intend to use
it for a כוי koy *koy*, and therefore we have this problem
of שחט *shecht*-ing the כוי koy *koy* because you won't be able
to use the ashes because that's not מוכן muchan. *muchan*. But according
to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, if dirt is available for everything, what's
the problem with שחט *shecht*-ing the כוי koy *koy*? You could because
dirt his whole point is כל צרכיו kol tzorachav *kol tzrachov*. Ashes
we never said כל צרכיו kol tzorachav, *kol tzrachov*, so we could
say those are only designated for the things you would most likely
expect, ודאי vaday *vadai* and not ספק safek, *safeik*. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says let's take a look. לספק מאי טעמא לאו *lesafeik
mai ta'ama lav*? So what's the reason that they're not considered... Now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* first didn't really understand the answer. It didn't
understand that it was a מוקצה muktzeh, *muktzeh* difference because as I
just said, what does it mean that it's not מוכן muchan, *muchan*
for ודאי vaday *vadai* but it is מוקצה muktzeh, *muktzeh* for ספק
safek, *safeik*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understood that the real difference
is are we going to allow you to scoop out the ashes?
So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, לספק מאי טעמא לאו דקעביד גומא
*lesafeik mai ta'ama lav deka'avid guma*? Maybe you're afraid that scooping out
the ashes makes a hole. ודאי vaday, נמי קעביד גומא *vadai nami
ka'avid guma*? So ודאי vaday. *vadai* also creates a hole. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אלא Ela, כדרבי אבא *ela k'deRabbi Abba*.
The hole isn't the problem because of like רבי אבא *Rabbi Abba*
said, which is a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה *melacha she'eina tzricha l'gufa*.
הכא נמי כדרבי אבא *hacha nami k'deRabbi Abba*. So you face the
same thing here. Again, quite strange גמרא Gemara *Gemara* because what do
the ashes have to do with making a hole, and we just
got through saying anyway it was a מוכן muchan *muchan* idea, not
a hole idea. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אלא ספק safek.
*ela safeik*. So again, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* should have shifted away
from the ashes and now it's really focusing much more again on
the digging of the dirt and the digging of the hole. Okay,
so let's now focus on that as the... because again, ashes ספק
safek? *safeik* versus ודאי vaday *vadai* does not make so much of
a sense, although we'll get back to that. אלא *ela* says... We'll
try again. ספק safek. מאי טעמא *safek mai ta'ama*, why is it
that by a כוי koy *koy* you cannot go ahead and cover
the blood if you שחט *shechted* it? דילמא הוי כתישה *dilma avei
ktishah*. Now we're getting back to what really makes sense as the
basis for distinguishing. Okay, if you שחט *shecht* the חיה chayah, *chayah*,
you'll have to cover the blood. Don't שחט *shecht* the כוי koy
*koy* and say I won't cover the blood, that's not acceptable either.
So don't שחט *shecht* either the חיה chayah *chayah* or the כוי
koy *koy*. If you went ahead and שחט *shechted* it, by the
חיה chayah *chayah* you can dig the hole, by the כוי koy
*koy* you cannot. And this is clearly the פשט *pshat* of the
ברייתא *braita*. Now we're getting around to that and saying okay, so
we're going to give you more latitude by the חיה chayah, *chayah*
than we are by the כוי koy *koy*. Let's see how that
plays out. The more latitude is, although digging the hole raises certain
problems, we'll turn a blind eye to it by the case of
the חיה chayah *chayah* when we won't by the כוי koy *koy*.
Okay, so it says like this, אלא ספק safek. מאי טעמא *elah
safek mai ta'ama*, why would we not let you dig a hole
by the case of ספק safek. *safek*? דילמא הוי כתישה *dilma avei
ktishah* because if you're digging a hole even though it's מלאכה שאינה
צריכה לגופה *melachah she'einah tzerichah legufah* and so on, but even though
it's loose dirt, there might be a clod of dirt amongst the
loose dirt and you'll come to pound it and pulverize it and
do a מלאכה *melachah*. So that's why if it's only a case
of a כוי koy, *koy*, we won't let you dig the hole
because it could lead to an accidental מלאכה *melachah*. בודאי נמי נגזר
משום כתישה *bevaday nami nigzar mishum ktishah*, let also not let you
do it in the case of the ודאי vaday, *vaday*. Now again,
the answer here seems obvious. There are some concerns, how much do
we override those concerns depends on how great the need is. If
it's a ודאי vaday. מצוה mitzvah *vaday mitzvah* of כיסוי הדם kisuy
hadam. *kisuy hadam*, we'll not be so concerned about it. We'll let
you do מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה *melachah she'einah tzerichah legufah*, we won't
be concerned you'll come to grind it if that happens. Whereas if
it's only a ספק safek. *safek*, we'll be more concerned. Seems like
a very obvious difference. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* somehow isn't buying into
it. If there's a concern that doesn't allow you to do it
in the case of a ספק safek? *safek*, it shouldn't allow you
to do it in the case of a ודאי vaday *vaday*.
There's no difference between יום טוב Yom Tov: *Yom Tov* and שבת
*Shabbat* in these מלאכות *melachot*, right?
In terms of the, other than אכילה *achilah*, right, defining the מלאכות
*melachot*, categories of the מלאכות *melachot* are not different. The difference is
whether it's if you're going to do it with צורך אוכל נפש
*tzorech ochel nefesh*, but the categories of the מלאכות *melachot* are not
different. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so no, ודאי vaday, כי
קעביד כתישה *vaday ki ka'avid ktishah*,
here's the difference. Not because we won't be concerned because you know
we're more, we more want to ensure you do the מצוה mitzvah.
*mitzvah*. No, but even if you went ahead and did the grinding,
עשה דוחה לא תעשה asei doche lo ta’asei *asei docheh lo ta'asei*.
You really wouldn't violate because you're doing a positive מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*
of covering the blood and that overrides the negative prohibition of יום
טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*. So here's a new idea. Not just
מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה *melachah she'einah tzerichah legufah*, maybe you could really
in principle, not we're going to allow it but in principle violate
יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* in order to do כיסוי הדם
kisui hadam. *kisuy hadam* because an עשה *asei* of כיסוי הדם *kisuy
hadam*, the positive מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* overrides the negative prohibition of יום
טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* quickly rejects
that. One minute, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, אימור דאמרינן *eimur de'amrinan*,
when do I say עשה דוחה לא תעשה *asei docheh lo ta'asei*,
that a positive מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* overrides a negative מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*?
כגון מילה בצרעת *kegon milah betzara'at*. Interestingly, we just had צרעת *tzara'at*
in the קריאת התורה *Kriat HaTorah*. Like you have somebody has a
sign of צרעת *tzara'at* on his foreskin. So therefore there's a negative
prohibition, השמר בנגע הצרעת *hishamer benega hatzara'at*, of removing from your body
the signs of leprosy, cutting them away. But there's a positive מצוה
mitzvah *mitzvah* of מילה *milah*. The very act of cutting the foreskin
does both. It does the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* of מילה *milah* and
it removes the צרעת *tzara'at*. So then the עשה *asei* overrides the
לא תעשה *lo ta'asei* because the one act that fulfills the עשה
*asei* is the same act that is violating the לא תעשה *lo
ta'asei*. That's when it's allowed. אי נמי *ei nami*, or here's another
example, שעטנז בציצית *shatnez betzitzit*. Linen in your ציצית *tzitzit*. Right, the
blue strand of ציצית *tzitzit* had to be wool and therefore if
you're wearing a let's say you know a linen garment, so putting
on that blue strand makes שעטנז *shatnez*, makes כלאים *kilayim*. But the
exact same act of wearing כלאים *kilayim* is the act of wearing
ציצית *tzitzit*. And therefore they're coming at the exact same time. That's
when the עשה *asei* overrides the לא תעשה *lo ta'asei*. דבעידנא דקמיעקר
לאו *debe'idna dekamia'kar lav*, when the לאו *lav* is being uprooted, not
violated because it's allowed to be done, it's being uprooted, קמוקמי עשה
*kamukmei asei*, that's the moment you're fulfilling the עשה *asei*. But הכא
*hacha* in this case, בעידנא דקמיעקר לאו *be'idna dekamia'kar lav*, when you're
violating the לאו *lav* like you're grinding
the what's it called the clod of earth into more granular, לא
קמוקמי עשה *lo kamukmei asei*,
you're not fulfilling the עשה *asei*. First you turn it into dirt,
loose dirt, and then you cover the blood. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is saying back to the question. Why will we allow you
in a case of a ודאי vaday *vaday* to dig the hole
and not a ספק safek. *safek*? So you say, well, there's problems
digging the hole, you might come to grind. So that should be
a problem in a case of a ודאי vaday *vaday* too. We
should be concerned about that. Ah, even if you did grind, you
wouldn't violate, עשה דוחה לא תעשה *asei docheh lo ta'asei*. No, you
would violate because the violation comes before the fulfillment of the מצוה
*mitzvah* of covering the blood. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
no, there could be a case where they come at the same
time. הא לא קשיא *ha lo kashya*, that's not difficult. You could
say that it wouldn't be a violation. Why? דבהדי דכתש קמכסי *debahadi
dechatash kamachasei*, it could be. As you are pounding the clod and
turning it into dirt, you're pounding the clod over the blood. Right?
You got the scenario, you got a clod of earth over the
blood, and you pound it, so the act of turning it into
dirt is the same act of covering the blood. Now the point
is, okay, that's a possibility, but that doesn't mean that that's definitely
what will happen. There's still the scenario where you would violate יום
טוב, Yom Tov. that you would first turn it into dirt and
then cover the blood. But let's see, the גמרא Gemara has a
different answer anyway. The גמרא Gemara says: סוף סוף, Sof sof, look,
bottom line, says the גמרא, Gemara this whole idea of עשה דוחה
לא תעשה doesn't work here, it doesn't play. יום טוב: Yom Tov,
עשה ולא תעשה. asei ve-lo ta’asei. יום טוב Yom Tov is not
only a negative command, לא תעשה מלאכה, lo ta’aseh melachah, it's a
positive command which is, you know, it says שבתון, Shabbaton, that it
should be a day of rest. So therefore it's a positive command
and a negative. ואין עשה דוחה לא תעשה ועשה. Ve-ein asei doche
lo ta’asei ve-asei. The positive מצוה of covering the blood doesn't override
the negative and positive of יום טוב. Yom Tov So that's not
an answer anyway. It's a problem, even if you manage to do
it at the same time, you cannot violate in order to cover
the blood. So if there's a concern that we won't let you
dig the hole by a case of the כוי koy and the
ספק, safek? that it could lead to violation, it should be an
equal concern by the case of the ודאי. vaday So we're back
to our problem. We got the idea that A, you could have
a box of dirt which you could use for anything. Ashes maybe
you could use for most things. Okay, but if you don't have
the dirt and you don't have the ashes and you only have
the option of digging the hole, so if by חיה chayah and
by כוי, koy don't do it, because we don't want you to
dig the hole. If you went ahead and did it, dig the
hole by the חיה chayah and not by the כוי. koy The
גמרא Gemara says, what's the difference? If the difference is a concern
that you'll come to violate, we should apply that to the חיה
chayah as well. Okay, so let's see where the גמרא Gemara says.
So אלא אמר רבא: Rava קירה. Kira. Forget about digging the hole.
Again, it was such a good explanation, you know, just because, yes,
in one case we'll be more concerned than in the other, because
one case there's a greater need in order to do a ודאי
vaday מצוה. But the גמרא rejects that whole explanation, and we get
back to the following: קירה דעתו לודאי ואין דעתו לספק. Kira da’ato
le-vaday ve-ein da’ato le-safek. What the גמרא seemed to be saying earlier,
now it's coming back to it. You have ashes, but as opposed
to a box of dirt which is good for anything, you have
ashes, the ashes you plan on using for things that have a
definite need, not things that are doubtful, which is another way of
saying, like I said before: ashes don't have a lot of uses,
so the only, you only have in mind the few standard uses
for them. You don't have generic use in mind. And therefore you
cannot use the ashes by the case of the כוי koy because
for the כוי koy they're מוקצה, muktzeh they're not מוכן. muchan, They're
only מוכן muchan, for a case of a חיה. chayah Again, very
funny that something is מוכן muchan for uses A, B, and C,
but not D, E, and F, even though D and F are
also reasonable uses. Okay, because those were more doubtful whether you would
have to have, use it for D, E, and
F. ואזדא רבא לטעמיה. Ve-azda Rava le-ta’amei. רבא Rava goes according to
his reasoning. דאמר רבא: De-amar Rava: הכניס עפר לכסות בו צואה, Hechnis
afar le-chasot bo tzo'ah, מותר לכסות בו דם ציפור. mutar le-chasot bo
dam tzipor. Now, if you brought in dirt to, again, your sort
of generic all-purpose dirt, and you were going to use this to
cover, like, excrement. Like, you know, you might have a little baby
who lays who poops around the house before an age of diaper.
And you want to use dirt to cover it up. So you
can also use it for covering the blood of a, this on
יום טוב, Yom Tov. it's not מוקצה, muktzeh. it's מוכן muchan for
covering the blood of a chicken if you שחט a chicken. Now,
if I ask you, you got a baby in the house and
you've got a chicken, which one is the ודאי vaday use you'll
use the dirt for and which is the ספק, safek, what would
you say? The baby is the ודאי, vaday. right? So the גמרא
is assuming the opposite. The chicken is the ודאי. vaday You're definitely
planning on having chicken for יום טוב. Yom Tov. The baby is
a ספק. safek, What's the ספק? safek רש״י says, well, depends if
he poops in a place where you, where it bothers you or
not. So definitely dealing with a very different reality. Okay, for some
case, the case of the covering the צואה, tzo’ah, the excrement, is
a ספק. safek So רבא Rava says, if you brought in the
dirt for things that you might, even had like a doubtful need
for, you can certainly use it for things you're definitely going to
have a need for, like covering the blood of the, of the
chicken. דם ציפור, Dam tzipor, if you brought it in the house
to use for covering the chicken, אסור לכסות בו צואה. assur le-chasot
bo tzo’ah.
You can't use it for covering the poop because that was not
things that you would have, not necessarily expected you would need it
for. So this is introducing this fascinating idea by מוכן. muchan Right?
Normally we understand it's either מוכן muchan or it's not מוכן. muchan
It's either מוקצה muktzeh or it's not מוקצה. muktzah, Here no, it's
מוכן, muchan and this also gets into the idea of defining מוכן
muchan, as a positive category rather than as מוקצה muktzah as the
positive category. If something has to be מוכן, muchan maybe could be,
maybe it's only מוכן, muchan and we get to like what I
would have been thinking, you know, what would have been my intention?
Only מוכן muchan for things that I the most, like the things
that I would normally use it for that would regularly come up,
not the things that would come up only rarely. Only מוכן muchan
for ודאי vaday. not ספק. safek So therefore, and that's the difference,
says the גמרא, you know, when רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says a
pile of dirt כל שהוא. kol-she-hu. presumably that's everything. Here's an approach
that's skeptical about that. The ashes, the dirt, maybe those are only
considered מוכן muchan for ודאי, vaday, not for ספק. safek And that
helps us explain why you can't cover the blood by this כוי,
koy. because ashes and dirt or whatever are only considered usable for
things that are normal regular uses, definite things you'll use it for,
not things that are less likely that you'll need them for. Okay,
so that's it's important for them to realize the bigger theme that's
going on in the גמרא is that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda introduced
this idea of a pile of dirt you could be עושה oseh
כל צרכיו. And כל צרכיו the גמרא latched onto it, anything? Anything?
What about the whole כוי koy case? Meaning and what's that opposing?
It's opposing an idea that even though we say ashes and dirt
set aside are not מוקצה, muktzah that doesn't mean you they're usable
for anything. It means that they're מוכן muchan for like for like
high likelihood uses, for ודאי. vaday They're not מוכן for ספק. safek
And that helps explain why you can't cover the case of the
blood of the כוי, koy because these things are considered מוקצה muktzah,
or not מוכן vis-a-vis that.
You no longer making a distinction between ashes and dirt? Right, meaning
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda seemed to be
saying dirt is better because dirt is any use, but now רבא
Rava, is saying, they're trying to bring this example of a כוי
koy, and there's a general approach that's saying, no, whether dirt or
ashes, it's a more limited set of usages that's מוכן, it's not
anything under the sun. Okay, now we'll keep on going but that's
exactly that theme. Can there be something like dirt, according to רב
יהודה, Rav Yehuda, that you can use for anything? Or is this
idea that no, all these things are ודאי vaday, but not ספק?
safek Right, so the גמרא says like this. נהרבלאי, Nahardelai, so נהרבלאי
Nahardelai Rashi tells us in a different גמרא is Rami bar Berabi
or bar Bruchi, so whatever that name means נהרבלאי Nahardelai says, where
are we? דף ח עמוד א. daf chet amud aleph. Okay, thank
you. אמרי נהרבלאי אפילו הכניס עפר לכסות בו דם ציפור מותר לכסות
בו צואה. Amri Nahardelai afilu hichnis afar lachasot bo dam tzipor mutar
lachasot bo tzoa. Even if you brought in the dirt for the
chicken blood, you can cover the poop. Now is that because in
principle he says that poop is also fundamentally he only lets you
use it for ודאי, vaday but he says covering excrement is close
to a ודאי vaday need? Or he could be arguing in principle
and saying like we said before, כל צרכיו, I don't believe that
just because you have one thing in mind you're you know it's
a small list of the things that you can use it for.
Whatever comes up? Exactly. So let's take a look. אמרי במערבא פליגי
בה רבי יוסי בר חמא ורבי זירא.
Amri b'Maarava pligi bah
Rabbi Yossi bar Chama v'Rabbi Zeira. So they say that in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael this is a debate of רבי יוסי בר חמא
Rabbi Yossi bar Chama and רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. ואמרי לה רבא
בריה דרבי יוסף בר חמא ורבי זירא. v'amri lah Rava breih d'Rabbi
Yosef bar Chama v'Rabbi Zeira. Some say רבא Rava. the son of
רבי יוסף Rabbi Yosef was the first מאן דאמר man d'amar and
he argued on רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. חד אמר כוי הרי הוא
כצואה, chad amar koy harei hu k'tzoa, one said, you gotta love
this comparison, a כוי koy. is like excrement. וחד אמר כוי אינו
כצואה, v'chad amar koy eino k'tzoa, it's not like excrement. What that
means is we're assuming again that everybody buys into
this idea that if it's set aside for something that's a ודאי
vaday use, you cannot use it for something that's a more doubtful
need. And the question though is, is that like a continuum, right,
of how definite and how doubtful? So apparently way at one end
of absolutely definite need, if I make chicken every יום טוב, Yom
Tov, is covering the chicken blood. Now a little bit closer, not
definite but in the, I don't know, 90 to 95 percent likelihood
is the covering of the excrement. כוי koy is maybe you know
somewhere over here like in the 60 percent or something. So that's
the discussion. Is כוי koy... like צואה? tzoa? How much is כוי
koy, a high enough likelihood of need that if I can use
it the same way if I set it aside for the blood?
It's assuming if I set aside for the blood why can I
cover the צואה? tzoa? Not because I don't buy into the distinction
of ודאי vaday and ספק. safek I do buy into that distinction.
I just say that צואה tzoa is so likely that it's close
to the ודאי vaday category. So now let's talk, is כוי koy
also close enough to צואה tzoa
close enough to the ודאי vaday.
category that I can use it for כוי koy as well? Isn't
that the same question? Because one is a likelihood of happening and
one is whether it's required when it does happen. I know, you
know, that's a very good point, which is you're absolutely correct. I'm
glad you picked up on that so I can't get one over
on you. As what I said before, like who the heck cares
that כוי koy? the obligation is ספק? safek. The need is ודאי.
vaday... As opposed to the case of the excrement where we're trying
to say that the need is a ספק, safek I might not
need it for it. Right? The כוי koy the whole question is
if I always at every יום טוב Yom Tov, have a כוי,
koy that's my special יום טוב Yom Tov, dish, then that's a
ודאי vaday. need even though the actual legal obligation is a ספק,
safek. the need is a ודאי. vaday Yeah, I don't know the
answer to that. It's so funny though, I'm glad you picked that
up though.
That's the thing you have to look out.
Yeah, that's why we're saying that the excrement is a קרוב לודאי.
karov l'vaday. So let's take a look. חד אמר chad amar one
says, כוי הרי הוא כצואה. koy harei hu k'tzoa. It's close enough
to the צואה. tzoa. It's כוי koy close enough of a high
likelihood of need and therefore you can use it for the כוי
koy as well. חד אמר, Chad amar, כוי אינו כצואה. koy eino
k'tzoa. It is not like the case of the צואה tzoa
because... now let's take a look. וחד אמר, V'chad amar, כוי אינו
כצואה. koy eino k'tzoa. That צואה tzoa now maybe again if you
say כוי koy? is כצואה k'tzoa maybe it's saying that you could...
that it could be a way of saying that fundamentally you disagree
and you could use it even for general ספק safek. cases. But
כוי אינו כצואה koy eino k'tzoa is clearly saying no. צואה tzoa
you can use it for, that's close to ודאי, vaday, כוי koy,
is much more ספק sofek case. תסתיים Tistayeim דראבא הוא דאמר d'Rava
hu d'amar כוי הריהו כצואה. koy harei hu k'tzoa. Let's say Rava's
the one that says כוי koy is like צואה. tzoa. Why? דאמר
רבא, D'amar Rava, הכניס עפר לחסות בו צואה hichnis afar l'chasot bo
tzoa מותר לחסות בו דם ציפור. mutar l'chasot bo dam tzippor. דם
ציפור Dam tzippor אסור לחסות בו צואה. assur l'chasot bo tzoa. That
if he put צואה tzoa clearly in a ספק sofek. category. He
says if you brought it in for צואה tzoa you can use
it for covering the chicken blood, but if you brought it in
for the chicken blood you can't use it for the covering the
צואה. tzoa. So for him, צואה tzoa is clearly in a ספק
sofek category, right? So if it's in a ספק sofek. category, that's
the same category as כוי. koy, So to say כוי koy, is
like צואה tzoa in theory allows for, you know, so... so that's
sort of... so there's a way of saying so כוי אינו כצואה
koy eino k'tzoa clearly lays out that צואה tzoa is you can
use it for, כוי koy, we know is something you can't use
it for, at least according to this approach right now, it's a
clearly a ספק sofek. category. So כוי אינו כצואה koy eino k'tzoa
means צואה tzoa is a much higher likelihood of use than כוי,
koy. and you can use this type of stuff for צואה tzoa
but not for כוי. koy, כוי koy is like צואה tzoa opens
up the possibility that to say you could either use it for
both or not use it for both but you treat it the
same way. And the גמרא is saying Rava is the one that
would say if you said you can't use it for צואה, tzoa,
so obviously כוי... so צואה... tzoa... so you can't use it for
כוי, they're in that same category of ספק sofek and not able
to be used.
Moving away from the concept of all-purpose dirt?
That's what the גמרא is saying, that was רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
about the box of dirt, and this is רבא, this is exactly
what is the debate that's going on here, why the גמרא pushed
against רב יהודה Rav Yehuda because it knows there's this other approach
that dirt and ashes and whatever can only be used for like
ודאי vadai and not ספק. sofek Okay? רב יהודה Rav Yehuda not
רבא.
Right,
רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, right. Okay, so now the גמרא says like
this.
Not any ודאי, vadai but specific purpose, not because it can be
multiple ודאיs. vadai.
Right, exactly. The ודאי vadai of כוי as... as we said is
a different type... the ספק sofek of כוי is different than what
we're really talking about, which is the ודאי vadai need for it
or not the ודאי vadai need for it.
But they're certainly going beyond the ודאי need, they're saying it has
to be for a particular
ודאי.
No, when it says ודאי... you know, oh, you mean in terms
of like the צואה? tzoa? No, because that's the question that maybe
צואה tzoa is not considered a definite need, it's a high likelihood
but not a definite need. I know, for us it's pretty funny
because we would consider צואה tzoa to be a ודאי. Okay. רמי
בריה דרב ייבא אמר. Rami brei d'Rav Yeiva amar. Okay, so now
we have basically one explanation of why not to cover, so back
to this issue. בדיעבד ושחט, B'diavad v'shachat, can you cover... you can
cover the blood of a חיה chayah, not of a בהמה, beheimah
why not of a כוי? The simplest answer is because digging a
hole raises problems which we'll turn up... which we'll ignore by a
case of a חיה, chayah we won't ignore by a case of
a חיה chayah, but it's not unproblematic. The גמרא for some reason
rejects that and says no, the reason here is is that you've
got dirt or you've got ashes, it's only a מוקצה muktzah, problem,
a מוכן problem, but this interesting idea not like רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda that something could be מוכן for certain issues and for certain
usages and not for others, מוכן for ודאי not for ספק. And
then we have to decide what's considered close enough to ודאי, what's
way over there in ספק. But anyway, that's the problem and therefore
it could be מוכן to cover חיה blood and not מוכן to
cover כוי blood. That's explanation number two. Now we're going to do
explanation number
three. רב ייבא אמר Rav Yeiva amar כוי היינו טעמא דלא מכסינן,
koy hainu ta'ama d'lo michassinan, here's the reason you don't cover the
blood of a... of a כוי on יום טוב. Yom Tov Has
nothing to do with digging a hole, has nothing to do with
מוקצה, muktzah you could have loose dirt, we could פסקן pasken like
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda that you could use that loose dirt for
anything, there would be no problem covering the blood, no מוקצה, muktzah
no nothing. But you still don't cover the blood on יום טוב.
Yom Tov, Why not? גזירה משום התרת חלבו. Gezeirah mishum hataras chelbo.
People will say, 'Oh, you're covering the blood of that animal, that
must mean that it's a חיה, that must mean that we can
eat the חלב.' chelev. Now כוי has the worst of both worlds,
it might be a חיה so you have to cover the blood.
It might be a בהמה behemah. so you can't eat the חלב.
chelev. If somebody sees you covering the blood, no problem in the
actual act of covering, the problem is it'll lead to people thinking
it's a חיה and they'll come to eat the חלב. chelev. הגמרא
HaGemara says אי הכי אפילו
בחול נמי, ee hachi afilu b'chol nami, so don't cover the blood
in a weekday either! People will make the same assumption in a
weekday if you cover the blood. הגמרא HaGemara says no, בחול אמרי
לנקר חצירו הוא דצריך. b'chol amri l'nakker chatzero hu d'tzarich.
In the weekday, if they see you digging and shoveling or whatever,
they're saying who knows what you're doing, you've got blood in your
ground and you're trying to clean up your dirt, your ground, you
don't want a bloodstain in the middle of your backyard, but they
won't think that it's a מצוה of כיסוי הדם. But if you're
doing it on יום טוב, Yom Tov then no, you're not allowed
to be... digging in your yard on יום טוב, Yom Tov. they'll
understand the only reason you're doing it is the מצוה of כיסוי
הדם. The גמרא says, שחט באפר מאי איכא למימר? shachat b'eifer mai
ika l'meimar? So let's say on a weekday, somebody שחט his this
כוי in the middle of a dung pile. So nobody thinks you're
cleaning up your dung pile. Okay? So they obviously know that you're
doing it for the מצוה. או בא לימלך מאי איכא למימר? Or
ba limalech mai ika l'meimar? Somebody comes to the בית דין beis
din and they say, do I have to cover the blood? So
how can we say yes, according to you, that making it clear
you're doing the מצוה makes people think you can eat the חלב,
cheilev, okay, then we should never be able to פסקן pasken to
somebody if somebody says to us, should I cover the blood of
a כוי? We should never be able to say yes, cause then
they'll say that you have to it's a חיה and you have
to eat the and you're allowed to eat the חלב. cheilev. So
how do you make sense of that? גמרא says no, here's the
explanation.
אלא, here's the explanation. בחול, B'chol, in a weekday, אי נמי מספקא
אמרי ליה רבנן זיל טרח וכסי. inami msafkah amrei lei rabbanan zil
tarch v'chasei. People get it. People say look, if he's covering the
blood in a weekday, wherever he's covering it, on a garbage dump
on a dung pile, the רבנן rabbanan told him to cover it.
People know that sometimes you have to do things להלכה l'halacha to
be מחמיר machmir because you don't know. So just because they see
him covering the blood, they'll assume why is he covering the blood?
Because it's a ספק and they won't come to eat the חלב.
cheilev. They know you do things sometimes because of ספק. But ביום
טוב, b'Yom Tov, people will say if he's covering it on יום
טוב, Yom Tov? אם מספקא im msafkah if the רבנן rabbanan had
a doubt how to categorize the כוי, מי אמרי ליה רבנן זיל
טרח וכסי? mi amrei lei rabbanan zil tarch v'chasei?
They never would have told him to go to expend this effort
on יום טוב and cover the blood. So the concern again is
is that people will see you covering the blood. If they covered
it on a weekday, they'll understand maybe you don't know what a
כוי is, whether it's a חיה or בהמה. behemah But if you
cover it on יום טוב, they'll say the only reason you would
violate not violate, but do such an effort on יום טוב would
only be
if you definitely had to cover as if it was a definite
חיה and that we can't allow because then they'll come to eat
the חלב. cheilev. Now of course, once you say that, you wonder
why we had to frame it as this question about what people
will misinterpret, because you are already reflecting a reality that people will
see you covering it and saying, you shouldn't be doing that on
יום טוב. So why shouldn't you be doing that on יום טוב?
We just got through saying it's not a מוקצה muktzah problem, it's
not a digging a hole problem. So the key word here was
the word זיל טרח. zil tarch. טרחא, Tircha, because you're expending effort.
So why didn't the גמרא just say that was the difference? We
don't want you to be you can do the טרחא tircha for
the ודאי מצוה of the חיה, and you don't do the טרחא
tircha for the ספק מצוה of the כוי, right? So couldn't it
have been that difference? With just a טרחא tircha difference? But apparently
no, that would not have led to us distinguishing between the cases,
but people will interpret that. And therefore people will say if you're
covering it, it must be it was a ודאי because otherwise you
wouldn't have done such a טרחא. tircha. And that's why we won't
let you do it so it's not misinterpreted. Okay, let's just finish
this up. תני רבי זירא, Tani Rabbi Zeira, לא כוי בודאי אמרו,
lo koy b'vadai amru, not only can you not cover up the
blood of a כוי, אלא אפילו שחט בהמה חיה ועוף ונתערבו דמן
זה בזה אסור לכסותו. ela afilu shachat behemah chayah v'of v'nisarvu daman
zeh b'zeh asur l'chasoto. Even if you have the blood of a
חיה and an עוף, of, which again you shouldn't be שחט according
to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, but okay, you went ahead and did
it, and you also have a little blood of a בהמה behemah.
mixed in, you shouldn't cover it ביום טוב. b'Yom Tov. Because presumably
you'll be doing a little extra effort for the blood of the
בהמה. behemah? So אמר רבי יוסי בר יסיניא, amar Rabbi Yossi Bar
Yasinaia, לא שנו, lo shanu, when is it that you can't be
doing it because of the extra effort related to the בהמה? behemah,
אלא שאין יכול לכסותו בדקירה אחת, Ela she'ein yachol l'chasoto b'dkirah achat,
that you can't do it with one shovel, meaning you need to
shovel more, and therefore there's a concern that you'll be doing extra
shoveling to cover the some of the blood that is not doesn't
need covering. אבל יכול לכסותו בדקירה אחת מותר, Aval yachol l'chasoto b'dkirah
achat mutar, if you can do it with one shoveling it's permissible
because then you're not doing any extra effort. So גמרא says פשיטא
pshita obvious. No, מהו דתימא ניגזר דקירה אחת אטו שתי דקירות mah
d'teima nigzar dchirah achat atu shtei dchiros maybe I won't allow the
case of one shovel because then we'll come to allow the case
when you need to do extra shoveling, which we won't let you
do because of the because that's blood of a בהמה, behemah? קמשמע
לן kamashmalan that we are not concerned with that. So I gotta
point out, the last thing the גמרא left with was a concern
of extra effort, right? What's the whole problem of covering the blood
of a בהמה? behemah If you've got the loose dirt and you've
got whatever, presumably we're back to the טרחא tircha issue. So that
really could have been the difference with the כוי, not just how
people interpret it. It could be the reality, you don't want to
allow that טרחא tircha for a ספק. We only want to allow
it for a ודאי. So at the end of the day we
have like three explanations why not the כוי. One is, which the
גמרא rejected which to me is the best explanation, which is digging
the hole is problematic, we're only going to allow it for a
בהמה not for חיה, not for a כוי, for a ודאי not
for a ספק. The other is a מוקצה problem, there could be
things like dirt and אפר which is not מוקצה which is מוכן
for things that are in a ודאי category not a ספק category,
although why a כוי is in a ספק if it's a ודאי
need is a question. And then the third explanation is
it's a טרחא tircha that we is more problematic in a case
of a ספק and even if that wouldn't make us make a
distinction, people will interpret it that way and therefore it'll lead to
allow. How much work do you have? You have two and a
half, wait, four pages? Let me look at your work. Oh, it's
okay, it's not actually that much. You can do it.
We start next session on Monday, 11:30. Good
luck on the rest of the week. You too. All right. Take
care. Bye-bye.